Yeah, you know, it could have easily broke the shelf and continued higher.
It just would have made this area even more weaker.
But in other case, it held the shelton didn't.
Why? Because the inventory of liquidity, but if you look at almost any midflow,
what I need to do is validate. This is a H4 shell.
So if you look at any midflow, here we flip the shelf, retested it, went into midflow,
last base push, held. Last base, base, held.
sideways a big sideway is draining the biliquity
drain the biliquity run
held the last base
fell to hold the last space
shift
yeah as soon as they got past that shelf
and you can actually see the volatility as well
price is stable
stable stable
and then as soon as they cross past the shelf
it won't always be like this
it's shut up yeah
right so sometimes price can't hang around the shelf
for a while
it can't hang around the shelf for a while
it can't hang around
the shelf retest for a while doesn't always have to accelerate through it but typically
because of the way large orders are filtered out into the market the last inventory is holding the
liquidity as and when price pushes through that last inventory it's because the the bulk of the
momentum liquidity holds the price of that price run is now weaker we can typically expect
basically it's the first sign of weakness we then get clear insight
compared to the stronger moves
if you look at this move which
continues
and moves 200 pips
it holds every single base
here we had our first
break of midflow
right this is the last base
that pushed it to new highs
we had a break of midflow
and then this pushed it to new highs again
we broke it again
and then it goes on it's like
it takes another leg higher
leaving this area of weakness
but what the point I would make here is
after the breaks of midflow
there's a lack of sustainability
in that price room
it doesn't often continue.
Whereas if you compare that to a price run,
which is mad strong,
like this one,
it holds almost every base
and it breaks it for the first time.
So it holds every last shell.
The one that pushed it to new lows,
holds it.
Pushed it to new lows, holds it.
This pushed it to new lows.
It holds it and will come back to it.
New lows, hold.
New lows for the first time we break
past the last inventory,
indicative of seven,
strength and cell momentum slowing down that's when after that you got the shot and obviously you had your
okay we had a bigger move yeah that was a mad paraparpolic leg that was but in other case i would
be looking to go along here and i'll be looking to push it past that area every single time most of your
price swings right most of the successful price swings will follow this pattern where you have liquidity
holding price down throughout the duration of its strength and then
As the momentum of that move dries off, price will break midflow and it will pop, leave in this area a week.
Now, you know, it's important to realize just because this is the sequence of events that takes place,
let's say, the big, big majority of favorable price swings doesn't translate into every single instance of break amid flow causing a reversal.
Yeah, of course.
It's just highly probabilistic.
So based on statistical inference, you'll see it happens.
over and over and over again on historical charts on live charts you will eventually build a
level of conviction in what you'll see you're a little subtle subtle pieces of information that
you know most people would consider as noise and because they classify as noise they don't even
look into these kind of things how subtle is this price simply breaking the last inventory
and from that we can retract or extract that the momentum of this move is slowing down you know
it happens over and over again
but that being said
it's important to realize
that
you know as we discussed time and time again
why these last similarities are holding
you know this move out
is a function of weak by liquidity
shot of market or the cells
cause the price to run up
now it initiates a price run with a bid's withdrawal
but the bulk of the liquidity
that wants to get filled
remains up here
yeah the origin
um not the origin
this is the last inventory oh yeah yeah okay uh the origin of this price run is here on a of the fractal
price tool i agree that'll be the fractal called aka origin um it doesn't have to go but if i show you
for example this one here if i show you this one here price sold up pushed to new lows
it didn't return to its origin yeah right what we saw is the sell liquidity become more aggressive
in chasing price of law.
Did you get it?
In both instances, though,
the last inventory held.
Do you get it?
So we don't class it as price returning
back to the origin
when we discuss a mid-flow
because the different variations
in mid-flow.
Here, prices are returning to shell.
Here, prices not returning to shell,
but in both instances,
the last shell came up.
Yeah. So we classify mid-flow
as a directional price move
of imbalance,
with the characteristics of a structure
is the inventory holds
that's pushing price for it.
The first break of inventory
shows a sign of the weakness of that momentum.
Over time,
what I would need to validate
so here's a statement
that I'm going to make
is when the first inventory breaks,
it typically won't continue
for a long while after that.
Okay.
So if a mid-flow,
let's find on.
So if we look at our mid-flow,
okay, we flip shelf here.
This popped new lows.
we clear the top side of the shelf
but reach quite deeply into it
which is indicative of
actually we poked past the show
even subtle information like that
just on a side note
is quite significant
because on the way down
when the midflow is strong
never mind poking past it
price hardly pokes back into
the shell right
because there's so much liquidity
they're holding price down
whereas then this is this price
to reach past the shelf indicative of weakness
and indicative of thin cell liquidity
yeah but anyway price for the shelf it runs okay here's your shelf retest here it pushes into
bullish mid-flow the last inventory that pushes into new highs we broke it if you look at it quiet
right yeah broke it and it continues again now this is a fractal swing itself yeah broke show
whatnot uh we ran down that price run itself would have its own show it'd have its own bearish mid
flow likely weakness in that bearish midfield quite
on so it likely broke bearish midflow multiple times surges lower sellers dry out price draws back
into shelf and very light volume very very light volume will draw back into range builds up and it
pushes and then it starts a new fractal price swing all within obviously the big price swing
anyway right so we had our first break in the midflow here price continues price continues
high becomes highly inefficient I would make the argument we'll have look at it just now
price breaking that low there
with that candle broke midflop
of this fractal swings
so all we'll have a look at that.
So there's the imagery that points it in your eyes
imagery that pushed into your eyes here
distinctively broke it, yeah?
Here's a big sideways.
Here's your search.
It's quite notably
more inefficient than
almost any of these other fractal legs
and then obviously
you had a shelf leg and reversal.
So yeah, it happens on a repeating basis.
and over and over again, price is fractal, it's ridiculously consistent.
It does not mean, though, that every single price swing that breaks that flow will reverse.
It doesn't mean that every single price swing that, you know, so there's going to be apexes.
Like, let's say, look at this.
You have one apex here, two apex is there.
Visually, they have different, you know, they're different.
Anatomically, they're different.
This is much more spike at the high.
This is a bit more, it makes multiple attempts to go higher this one, though.
In either case, the characteristics are the same.
Yeah.
Think about it.
this way, both of these look, and it's not enough data to make a definitive, you know, to make
a definitive observation based off, because it's only two instances. But in both instances,
the high health, the apex retest held. This one just had a deeper apex retest. Do you mind
just zoom in a little bit, please? Which, yeah. Oh, yeah, that's better. Yeah. Both apex test,
held, and both of them successfully flipped the shelf and went into bearish midfield.
The point I would make is
a vast majority
of the successful apex
that do result in shell
with reversals and shards
are going to be the ones
that have the favorable characteristics.
They can look different
anatomically.
They will be different variations.
This one makes multiple attempts
to go higher.
It actually holds
inside the shelf
for a slightly longer period of time.
This shelf is slightly further away
from the high.
The shelf is really quite close.
this shelf is really quite close
this one only makes really one test
this shelf and draws back in then pushes through
this one
it would test a fractal shelf
then it goes deeper then it goes deeper
and then it pushes through
you get it
yeah so so in that one there
would you say that
when it goes up it absorbs
any of the cell liquidity
on the top
yeah it's definitely picking out
this one right
yeah that's the one yeah it's definitely
grabbing the same
sell liquidity. So imagine, you know, there's
a hundred millionaire, some of this
following price down, that leg is coming back up,
reloading, reloading, reloading,
it's definitely doing it. Yeah, this
is the kind of ones that you say
can scare you?
Yeah.
100%.
So, it's
important that we look at the characteristics
of the favourable, you know,
price swing features, which is either
apex, mid-flow, or price-wing stages, the apex, the
midflow, the shelf flip, et cetera,
rather than having quite strict expectations for exactly how it should demand up.
Yeah.
You get it?
You said that in your process video.
All right.
Perfect.
Because what you don't want is to have stringent expectations.
It results in, put it this way, there's many different ways price can run.
In bullish midflow, it can run in a more efficient way.
It can run in a highly efficient way.
where we break a fractal shelf of this of this small swing
that says a one minute swing
we break a one minute shell
it doesn't even fill back to the people's inventory
and it continues off the middle of the price room
we know that middle of the price run
has residual liquidity which is weak
in a highly highly inefficient price room
price will continue after fractal legs
residual liquidity and just push the new highs time and time again
you get it
so if you saw this in isolation
it would seem as if
you know by isolation
I mean you didn't know
anything else around it
didn't look at the context
around it
it would seem as if
the residual level
pushed it to your eyes
just like here
for example
if we ignore everything
that's a residual level
yeah
and it pushes to your eyes
but when you contextualize it
this high is technically
hidden
it's not either on a bad level
but
it's just
continues
it's not the greatest
levels but
that's the shifting
point
in this instance
it hits the middle
of the price run
of this fractal run
and it continues
to me highs
when you contextualize it
the point I would raise
here is that we are
still in a
broader price room
and we would expect
the fractal runs
inside of it
basically a lower
time frame
shelf has no
influence on the higher
time frame
yeah
the price is in a
one hour price
room, this is a one hour line, you will see many lower time frame
apex formations and shell flips that failed to materialize in the bearishment
flow time and time again. Yeah, but it's not until the big shelf is flipped is when.
Yeah, if it's a H1 price run, you need a H1 shelf flip. Yeah.
In either instance, right, you know, when we have a one minute shelf clip or a five-day
shelf flip there, price fails to fully fill in the run of, you know, this 500 price run.
and it consistently holds the last inventory there's a principle we can extract from this the higher
time frame takes precedence or the high time frame governs lower time frame and by that what i mean is
or the high time frame pulls more liquidity as well so those those principles you want to write down
they're related to each other high time frame pulls more liquidity high time frame governs lower time
the point I'm making here is
this last inventory
when this didn't happen
this last inventory was holding the H1
the bulk of the liquidity
of this whole price from the website
so until the bulk of the liquidity
of the H1 run dries off
and it shows weakness
any fractal price run breaks
or somewhat inconsequential
they don't really matter that much
or at least they are not going to combat
a H1 midfield
What they do do, though, they are significant
because it's that fractal price runs
shell fit, which is what I would use
if I was short here to try and fill this extension
back to this height.
Yeah.
If I'm looking to fill this extension,
back in the way it would do, wouldn't it?
Say again?
It's all you would try and look to fill
until it actually fills.
If the model I'm implementing
is trade counterflow of this H1 abolishment field,
I would be looking to fade this fractal leg.
Then, you know, the keyboard here is fractal.
It has all the price swing features, you know, just like any price swing.
This itself would be a complete price swing.
I could expect the complete features to turn up.
As long as they're favorable, as long as each of those characteristics,
each of the components in that price wing remain favorable.
So the apex that forms at this high has the characteristics of all favorable apex.
if the shell clip that occurs
isn't a shitty shell clip
if the bullish midflow in this price room
it has a nice break of midflow
and then a pop
I'm talking about this 5 minute price room right
yeah
you know if all of the pricing features
maintain favorability
and then we get that sideways pot
at this fractal apex here
you know I'm looking for that
five minute run to break down
hence I need to use that 5 minute
show. But what I won't do
is use that 5-minute shelf as validation to hold
for a H-1 reversal, which is just course.
So the principles here are
high time frame pulls more liquidity. So essentially the high time frame
govern the lower time frame. If prices in a daily swing
does a H-4th shell clip matter? Not that much.
If prices in a
five-minute price swing, does a
30-tick chart shell-flip matter? No.
Yeah. Do you get it?
Yeah, yeah, that makes sense.
so here what we would have had is a five-minute shelf flip
when in reality you can you know
this could be classed as let's say a 15 minute price
right yeah
it's not always going to be that clear
I'll give you another example
here we flip this shelf
which is clearly the inventory of that
small run there
if we wanted the largest swing
to reverse
the shelf is obviously
that
yeah
there are the largest
swing would have drawn back up then you would have got your reversal so relative to the
time frame that the swing is present on we view it you know independently on that time frame
that's the next principle view your price swings relative to the time frame they're present on
one minute swing has one minute features the daily swing has daily features now over time you
will build a like an intuitive feeling to to rely on information on different timeframes
So it won't just be that systematic
It won't just be look for a daily shelf tip on a daily price swing
You'll be using fractals to time your entry
To get the most optimal entry even if it's a daily price room
So for example
If I just go to the HR
We have this pretty mad swing here
It's kind of ties back into the previous point
It's made
Here's a daily shelf clip
If I want to go short I'm not going to fucking wait
The price to break down here
And then look for for you know short
what I want to be doing is anticipating the end of this price swing quite early on where
you know here we had our low shelf plate price retested the shelf and it continued from
the bullish milk flow quite a strong one all by basis held yeah all by basis hold but here
we had quite a distinctive sideways and what we know in that sideways is it's draining a
bi-liquid is having multiple pick-offs multiple pick-offs draining the inventory and then it
did pop into a more parabolic phase as well.
That parabolic phase, if you look at it,
it's an individual price swing.
You break it down on the granular scale.
It breaks midflow quite early.
It has a sideways pop.
And then you can just imagine this in and of itself
is its own fractal five swing.
And we do the same thing there.
So once I'm able to, you know, think about it,
after sideways comes what, the pop.
Yes, sideways pop.
You know, it happens time and time again.
here it wasn't that distinct
to be clear but on the lower time frame
we did the sideways
then it did go to the loose
so if after the sideways
we can anticipate the parabolic phase
to lead the final run
before price draws back
into the shelf and hopefully reverses
then it makes sense to focus
on that parabolic phase
and it tried to time this ending
so we view it in isolation
to the time frame that's present on
this is a daily run
this is a H4 run let's say
this is a daily run that's a H4 run
and then we look at
for exhaustion on that H4.
Do you get it?
So we're given a location and a context
to where the swing is.
That's kind of contradictory
to the previous principle by the phrase
that we should view the price swing independently
to the time frame is on.
So it's important to realize
why we view it independently.
There's conflicting scales.
Here we have a daily swing
with multiple smaller swings inside of it.
You can imagine
the lower the time frame we go,
the more conflicting scales do are.
So in order to
to solve that problem of not getting mixed off with a, let's say, a four-hour shelter of the
four-hour swing, you know, we don't want to use that four-hour shelter to go turn into a daily
bearish, have a daily bearish bias, for example.
So to avoid that happening, we apply this principle to view price when you're related to the
time frame in the present. But in terms of selecting trades and timing trades, we have to be
aware of the way the time frame, sorry, where the price frame fits inside the border context.
This price swing is in the parabolic after the sideways phase,
parabolic phase of this larger price swing.
Yeah.
You get it.
This price swing here and the one down and the one up and the one down
are all within the sideways phase of the larger swing.
So here you have, let's just call it shelf,
price broke midflow here, pop lower, that's the large sideways.
There's your shelf.
Price gets above shelf, retest it, run the embellish midflow.
and hopefully he has a few breaks here
sideways and then pop
we know after the pop
we can expect liquid
it's not guaranteed but we would anticipate
of a lot of sample that this
the by liquidity in this infantry here is weak
as price approaches it it shouldn't have enough power
to push the new highs
it couldn't make multiple attempts
it'll go all the way back up
but you know we want to see weeks
as a nutshell
so you know in life time
when the price ring is unfolding,
it could be anywhere along this series of price swing stages.
So the sideways,
which includes the break of the midflow typically.
It doesn't have to.
You can have break amid flow all the way back up here.
Yeah.
You could have a break of midflow up here,
and then price can continue lower than this and sideways.
Every time you again have to build your intuition,
your skill in seeing this.
You will be able to just take a lot of examples.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
your parabolic phase and then price drawing back in into the shelf and building up that's the apex formation including the parabolic phase then you have your shell flip and then your shift mistake liquidity which is price going into polishment flow each of these are individual stages we need to you know give each of these individual stages a name basically so we can differentiate between the various environments that price can go into
in other case it can be a driven state or a more stable state
but think about this this mid-flow state is a bit more stable than the parabolic state
even though both of them are driven so you know from that you can extract a bit of
information that you know this the common way of describing price environments is
calling them either trend or range but what I've just said
here is we have one trend and two
trends but they're entirely fucking different
one of these trends here is highly highly
inefficient and one of them is
relatively stable or it's less inefficient
you can even call it modestly
efficient right
and treading under these conditions
here you could take extension
fields back to the previous high
here you can't really do think anything
over then trying to get to that high
yeah trying to go to the top yeah
so the point I'm making here is
These relatively broad, oversimplified ways of catapides in price or price environments,
they're not appropriate for price.
We can try to break it down the more granular scale, which gives us, you know, from that,
we see price in a better light or in a more accurate light.
We can trade it in a better way.
We can identify the most appropriate way to trade various environments.
One thing remains true in all markets is, and especially as markets evolve,
price environments are changing relentlessly.
Price is always going from stable to an efficient, to a bit less efficient, to a bit less inefficient, to more stable, to highly stable, et cetera.
It's always changing.
Those changes in environments, however subtle, will directly affect the way you trade price.
The levels you can use, the duration of the trade that you're likely to get, the duration of the response, how big the response is likely to be.
And then based of that, you have to manage the trade in various different ways.
the frequency of trades you're going to get
here you can be
you're going to get a high frequency of trades
even of shit levels
and the duration of your response is going to be quite big
again big big fields and etc
here not getting that much
at least in the first few days
you didn't get anything here
in the following few days
there was only two trades in these days
yeah you'd only get something there if you was like a
breakout trade or something when you
no
can you see here
price ran and it ran
it closed at the highs
nothing
then the following week
that was a Friday
this is Monday
Tuesday
this is a Monday
that's Tuesday
Friday
what happened is
we
the price slow down
of it basically
we had this highly
driven pop
the previous Thursday
and Friday
and then every morning
we would fill back down
90 pips
and I continue
there was only
two good trades
that day
it was to fill
that first extension
through Asia High back in
and then try to buy it up.
You'll get all your work done for the whole week
in the first two days, I'm fuck off.
How do you remember this from October last year?
That's crazy.
That's because I track the price.
I'm very, very closely connected to tracking price.
That's crazy how it was a whole year ago.
You remember it?
Yeah, if you look at the day, the 13th of October,
that's going to be a Sunday.
day and then the day closed on the 14th of October 9 p.m., which is Monday.
But anyway, what was it talking about?
So, yeah, the price environment is always changing, simply calling something a trend,
isn't a grandeur enough level to, you know, the point to make here would be subtle changes
in price delivery or the intensity of price movement can drastically affect the way we can trade
or the way we have to trade it.
Right, here you can be quite active looking for extension fills.
try to take an extension fill on this day here
or sorry on this day here
you didn't get anything
a price rolled past there like two 300 pips
and then came back the following day
yeah right
so even swiftly changes in price delivery
can affect the way you can trade
so simply calling something
a trend of the range isn't appropriate
hence why we look to break things down
on a more grander level so
you know I was trying to get into a price swing
you have a trend during the mid-flow stage
you have a stable area during the sideways stage
and you have a trend during the pop stage
but the intensity here is highly inefficient
versus relatively stable
that will have an influence on the way we can trade
so not only does
assessing the price swing stage
help us anticipate what price might do next
but it also helps us
identify the marking environment of prices in
and try we can look to trade that appropriately
In other words, if prices embellished midflow, I'm looking for a certain type of midflow
to trade against it, but in other case, I'm not going to look for huge reversals.
I'm going to look for short extension.
If price has done the sideways stage, let's say this is a daily chart, it's a daily price.
In this sideways stage, that's a huge price went to the downside, huge price on up,
the residual levels are responding, so the middle levels of these factors, they're responsive.
The apex retest are all, the swing retest, the apex is they all,
working, et cetera, et cetera.
And then the characteristics will change.
Price goes into parabolic phase
and it goes into a much more driven, inefficient state of liquidity.
Yeah.
Right.
If we're using price-fing stages to anticipate what price should do next,
after the sideways stage of a huge sample,
you will find that price does pop into parabolic stage.
You would actually be looking for, you know,
changes in the state of liquidity early on.
You'd actually be anticipating that price might accelerate here,
what the implications of the acceleration are on my trading
what you have to do, what you shouldn't do, et cetera, et cetera,
of a vast amount of experience that there is McLean.
I will be getting you to try and fade a highly inefficient run.
You're going to experience the pain.
I will be getting you to try and fade a relatively stable run.
You'll experience the type of leeway it gives you to take trades.
You're going to be interacting with a price on a mass scale
in all of its environments
to better connect with the appropriate dynamics
of volatility, state liquidity and price behaviour.
Before you can do that, you need to be able to assess price,
hence while we're talking.
You have to be able to accurately contextualize price,
what price is doing, where price is,
so the quality of the interactions you have is higher or great,
you know, it's a better quality.
It wouldn't make sense to just go out and identify ranges, for example,
when ranges can be of a wider
volatility, you know,
they can be greater volatility
inside of these ranges
or in the practice and price swing.
You can have extremely stable ranges.
You can have highly, highly inefficient price swings
and you can have modestly efficient price swings
or midflows as well.
If we, you know, if you didn't assess that
and I just told you to go straight out
and start trading in all midflows,
what you would find is that sometimes
trading against the midflow works
sometimes it doesn't
you wouldn't really have the framework
to differentiate between the different types
of midflows if we didn't discuss it
so I'm raising an importance
of not only assessing the price swing stage
but assessing the price delivery as well
how price is moving
it's a key key key component
in assessing price swing environment
or just the market environment
the price swing stages
are a key key key component
in assessing what price is likely to
next based on huge huge vast samples of price rings that have occurred for the last 20 fucking
years right on the smallest of scales on the biggest of scales they occur over and over again
we're taking that structure breaking down to pieces so we can better assess where along that sequence
of events we along these price and prices in lifetime so in other words here we just started
sideways and a pop we know what happened next but you know we had a sideways and a pop now this is
your big shelf right it would make sense of the big shelf at this stage you know just simply
using price swing stages that you know price to flip the shelf and go into bearishment flow
they flips the shelf and goes to the bearish middle flow yeah it's just a very selective example
that I'm using it where prices right now we broke this daily shelf and prices return back up
for an apex three test swing apex free test of the breakout accumulation that's technically what prices
done. But I could raise a case
for you that the higher, you know, this is a daily
chart. You know, higher
time frame governs lower time frame or it takes
precedence of the lower time frame.
On the weekly chart, there's
greater evidence to say that the
sellers are weak. So quickly
show you. So, just
look at this price swing from the high
to the low quickly.
So we
run, run, run. First break,
in midflow there. Another break
in midflow there. A distinct
to make it flow there, sideways
and a huge, huge, huge pump.
That's the last imagery that posted to new lows.
It looks like it's washed, isn't it?
Exactly.
So, these are all areas a bit of thin and washed.
And then we just come and grab the top side of it again.
I wouldn't expect it to be a huge bunch of sell liquidity there.
And if they were, you know, because it's a weekly,
you know, higher time frame pours more liquidity.
So even the washed area is on a higher time frame
will have some, you know, significant liquidity there.
Yeah.
where you'll get price responsiveness,
but I wouldn't expect to move to get powered like that.
What can't happen is, though,
a weak sell liquidity base here, a shell flip,
and then we have this factor A to B,
that has a shelf fit there.
In the event that price gets beneath that shelf,
it could just result in the bids given in
and price drawing lower defined by liquidity.
That doesn't take anything away from how weak this area still remains.
Once we reload off this better level,
I'd be expecting it to rip.
or they could just maintain
his ground and hold his ground here
and work his way through
and pop through
any of those instances
are possible.
Do you get it?
The high time from taking precedence here
is that we had a shelf
technically I would draw that
as a weak shelf.
We technically broke the shelf
and this air is all washed.
I expect there to be
significant high time from some weakness
common
at least 150
it's quite a big
and it could take
the next 18 months
to get there
quite easily
it could take 18 months
to get there
we could even
maintain a range here
the rest of the year
to March next year
take a dive
then drawback
or it could do any number of things
but I still expect
to sell you to determine
so anyway
what am I doing
I'm using the price swing stages
to set relative
expectations
for what price might do
based on my understanding
of price well
my conviction
in price for inconsistency
i.e, I believe
even if it happens over and over again
because I've seen it happen over over again.
I apply this framework.
It's just something that you won't have
the necessary conviction in
until you see over and over a little.
Just like anything,
I could tell you, no,
I don't know if you know about Plato's K thingy,
but what's that?
Plato's cave.
I don't know if it's a story or what,
but the whole crux of it is,
whatever you see is your reality.
So if you consistently see
certain price behaviors work over and over,
again it will become ingrained in your brain you will internalize it and depending on the level of
intensity or yeah the level of intensity of the way you engage those price behaviors you will identify
like exploitable behaviors as well an exploitable behavior for example would be this large
extension got filled right and then this extension has already been failed
can just imagine
if price
extends past there
or what happened
price extended
past these highs
it filled
price extended
past this low
it filled
price extended
past this low
it filled
right
it consistently
fills extensions
another
exploitable
price behavior
would be
core areas
of liquidity
are quite
responsive
right
you have this
core area
price
responded
there
you have that
core area
price
responded here
you had
it did respond inside
this high
it just doesn't look like it
it did
on this time frame
can't see it
but on the lower time frame
you would see that
price did respond
before pushing through
but yeah
so price responds
of course areas of liquidity
or broadly
price responds
of liquidity bases itself
so here you have
a liquidity base
here you have
areas of liquidity
price responded of it
I guess here you have
a large liquidity base
price responded off it
liquidity base
this one didn't
well
defined why you know that one was that um the flash crash not we have had no flash
flash crash this year it was coronavirus oh that was corona okay that was a march this year
coronavirus the flash crash that you might be referring to was in january the third
2019 or 18 can't believe i forgot let me check quickly there was a flash crash at like 10 p m on gm
on gm t u sd or 11 p m on g t yeah it was not near enough everything i think
on January
yeah
hell
oh that was it
okay
it happened
on the third of January
it sold off like
massive
yeah it was in the matter
of minutes
yeah
late in the night
it popped down
175 pics
so yeah
what we're talking about
so
do you think the coronavirus
just accelerated
the parabolic
phase
yeah
the effect of the coronavirus
was that
the initial
spike in bol
that we saw in the first few days, let's say, coupled with the narrative, resulted in bi-liquity, not turning up. It just wasn't present. If there was bi-liquity here and there was large entities, let's say normally there would be pension funds, hedge fund, future funds, large institutional investors for logistical purposes that are transacting at these level, they just didn't turn up. They were not transacting at these levels. And simultaneously, what you saw is heavy one-directional volume. So, it was a whole.
let's give you an example let's say one firm wise price was going up here built upon exposure of gvp of 600 million
in the event of the after the narratives comes out around coronavirus etc etc let's just say
those lungs start to peak they all go short just to cut the exposure so you have
extreme hedging going on here and there will be speculative entities at least
fast money HFT type entities that are trying to exploit this move down so they know
sellers are coming in they'll try to reach by liquidity before the sellers and then
buy a back at a lower price jump the queue basically in liquidity and you see heavy
directional one and as on top of that if you did have let's say one or another
firm who had a bearish view on a pound
that liquidity that they would normally transacted
through it in a passive way
sought to aggressively chase price as well
so you have a compound effect on volume coming in
and equity coming in with one direction
with huge huge amounts of weakness on the other side
right so you have much much bigger moves that occur
under event driven sentiment shifting events
here's one we had one here last year
when there was a basically they were
going to try to solve Brexit.
We were going to leave.
There was like a deadline approaching and then they solved.
It was a deadline approaching like right now,
like the condition we're in right now.
And then one day, I think it was a Thursday,
news came out that, yeah, we're going to fucking solve.
We're going to sit down and reach a solution or resolution.
There was a sentiment here, a massive one,
when the US interest rates
were expected to be too low for inflation
which would basically support USD
they're going to have to increase interest rates
and the market just went berserk
if you go a long US dollar across everything
and then obviously you can just imagine
there was a huge sentiment driven
it was already in line with poor the sentiment
but preceding that you had a huge move to the upside
it was a short-term sentiment shift
a huge huge one Brexit
and then if you go back to 2008
you had a credit crisis here
so the fastest
of moves you get on a higher time frame
they're all driven by events
and when those events are dry off
and they're all in the fucking
history box this is what price
is much more stable
even if you look at the characteristics of the individual runs
yeah they're made the big
price is running big big mounts here
but they're not inefficient
broadly
even this run is
sideways
then drop then sideways
then drop then sideways then drop
whereas moves like this
you'll see in massive
massive direction on moves
and short sideways periods
so we'll discuss
what goes on here but broadly
just from basic
you know where you can see visually
event driven environments
they run there's a huge amount of volatility
but they don't last that long
and for the most part
price remains and maintains stability.
Even if this moved down, it's a massive move for almost a whole year.
It wasn't exactly that inefficient.
But I would still class it as part of one of these event-driven sell-offs.
But then when prices isn't in one, which is a good vast majority of the time,
prices just stable all the fucking time.
Obviously, you had coronavirus here.
Why is price stable most of the time?
Well, the reasons for clients demanded liquidity isn't speculative.
They all don't just one type of client and ethics, right?
You know, like you said, there could be this two-sided liquidity demands for FX peers,
especially major peers, because you have vast, vast global, you know, capital flows in both economies.
Different types of investors look at different, looking for liquidity for different reasons,
for hedging purposes, operational purposes, et cetera, et cetera.
It was, and the way they trade is one looking for minimizing cost.
costs. You know if you're putting through
$30 billion of volume a year
even saving
0.2% on your commissions
or your market impact, your execution
cost is significant money.
Especially if you're
a CEO or a shareholder
in that firm,
as much costs as you save
has a direct effect on your
bonuses. So there's always been a cost
cost and culture. There's a huge
focus in effects as they exist today
on a market structure level.
For clients who buy liquidity, buy side, demanding ways to reduce market impact and transaction costs.
That's why a vast majority of trade or large, not a vast majority,
vast majority of large trades that are traded on electronic platforms are done through automated execution outgoes.
Yeah. You know, the execution algorithm is the high footprint, to hide the impact, hide information.
they don't just fill a $50 million order in one ticket.
They break into small pieces.
They try hide it.
To try even fill it over different exchanges or venues.
It just depends.
There's very different ways.
But the whole purpose of minimizing market impact and reducing costs has a direct impact
to the types of volatility we see.
The most volatile periods are event-driven.
They all still follow price swing features, by the way.
They're still sideways and pops and whatnot, but big, big sideways compared to the
seller. Seller basis of all
holding here is quite surprising actually
and then for the first time
if you look at it's quite subtle
this one push it to new lows
and then it broke and then here you have
quite a little surge coming to shelf
sales to push to new lows builds
build breakout accumulation
massive response later on
push it through it's nothing
yeah
it's much consistent though
but after that high high volume period
as we know, very little volume
low, high, high volume,
price volume,
sorry, market volume stabilises.
After any shot of high volume,
volume stabilizes.
All the time.
High, high, high shot of cell volume,
price stabilizes.
So that is a consistent European pattern.
It's actually an exploitable price behavior,
which again ties back into
this topic of discussion
where you're kind of having now.
You're going to have it.
price behaviours that you see repeat over and over and over again they consistent
repeat forever and ever and never they are exploitable if you see them happen
over and over again that becomes your reality like the Plato okay and based
of your own like repeated based of like your own experience of things
you'll have a deeper conviction especially if you view price in a structured way
you're seeing and hopefully look to extract and exploit price behaviors which are true we know why
these price behaviors exist so it's just all the basis of building a foundational understanding
then validating basically is what I'm saying you see happen up and over again you trust it
you have a conviction in it these two alone bridge the gap the vast you know that big
ambiguous psychology issue that all retail traders have all all traders have a big part of that gap
you don't even talk about psychology anymore as much at least we don't yeah and in my opinion as well
you know if we go back to this example how I said there's different variations of the same
trends you can have a highly inefficient trend and it stabilizes in the tempo and rhythm changes
and then here it starts off obviously it's in a range it pops out then it stabilizes it
then it fucking goes berserk,
the temper of ridden's always changed.
Even though they're moving in the same direction
in all these instances,
a few days later, the tempo of rhythm's changed.
That would have an effect on the types of trades you can take.
Imagine you're over-optimized the trade in this environment.
In other words, let's say this environment here,
you were going long using the last inventory,
just for an example.
Prices coming back into last inventory, you're going long.
Go along.
And then the environment changes.
You're trying to use the last inventory here.
and price is doing that against you get it yeah in these in these couple of days price was
massively drawing back down massively i'm telling you 90 clips every month you get it yeah
the market environment or at least the tempo the state of liquidity is changing if one has no
framework to assess changes in volatility or environment or liquidity state what's the first thing
that people can blame oh i should have stopped trading oh should have uh
do you get it
my risk management isn't good enough
oh no bro
like you just haven't got
an appropriate framework
for something that's highly dynamic
it's always changing
it's changing subtly
do you get it
yeah I don't see how people
can have a simple
say that the markets are simple now
they're really not
you know like they're just not
I will always say your strategy
your strategy can be simple
my strategy is area of strength, move of weakness,
I look for my imaginable response, that's it.
Yeah, your strategy can be simple, but the markets aren't simple.
But the market is not.
Wow, that is mental.
I caught this with, believe it or not,
I had a buy a limit order here.
Price hit my limit order, didn't fill,
gave me positive slippage and filled me at the exact log.
That's nice.
The exact low.
But I closed it here.
38 pips.
The problem is, I think...
Yeah, how can we close it in there?
Because I was calling on this call.
I had a 2.6-pips stop.
Well...
308 clips, 2.6 pips.
Wow.
I'm not lucky to be spectacular,
but I don't want 100 pitch.
You get it.
If you can make 7-R,
not even on average,
like, if you can make 7-R
10 times a month, bro,
you're a genius.
Like, you're in the realm,
of returns of like being classed as fantastic.
Do you get it?
You're in that realm,
in it?
You don't need to be any more fantastic than that.
Yeah, that's true.
Then the only thing that is,
that matters is how much risk did you have on that trade?
Yeah.
Or you're risking two pound or you're risking two thousand.
There's a huge difference.
You eventually want to build up to be able to stomach that risk,
but that's, again, through interaction and consistent engagement.
But I want to circle.
back to this point in making, yeah? So validating
validating price behaviors is necessary. But
what is this frame I keep talking about to actually
assess price? How do we, how do we, how do we, how, how,
what gives us the capacity to be able to assess changes in price
environment, to assess changes in price delivery is first of all
giving it actual, let's just call it a language to describe things.
Do you get it? Okay.
If we didn't deliberately differentiate and have a differentiating word for an inefficient environment
or, let's say, a fast environment versus a slower one, we wouldn't have the capacity
to at least identify and, you know, we wouldn't, it basically adds two extra words to our vocabulary
and two extra things we have to assess.
But assessing those two extra things, the quality is that we can trade more appropriately.
And then we also have to give them
characteristics. So characteristics are
you know, the, I guess
the visual features
of what's the definition
characteristics? Come on. Let me quickly change.
I know what you know what I mean, but
Yeah, you're trying to get a spot on definition.
Yeah, so a feature or a quality
belonging to something, right?
A property of it. So looking at the properties
of a fast and efficient environment, it will be
short extension fields or hardly fucking
filling the extension back to the inventory.
Sometimes
not even
yeah so sometimes in the
fractal swing not even responding
of the residual liquidity of this down need
and continuing to new lows. The lows
aren't holding and typically
it'll be to be residual liquidity. I know this
is core but typically it'll be to be residual
liquidity of a price rate. They're the
visual properties or components
or characteristics of an inefficient
fast mid-flot
and then the property of the visual
characteristics of a visual, you know, let's say a slow or more efficient midflow would be
larger extension bills, price draws back, you know, this greater volatility and how far back
price draws back. The fractal swings are more defined, et cetera, et cetera. That itself alone,
now you can, as Zane, if I told you, okay, you need to go out and try to find the most
appropriate way to trade midflows, now you have a basis to
appropriately differentiate between better midflows to trade and
a bit shitting midflows to trade. You can make the argument that
if you're a breakout trader, you want to be only trading on the disk
midflow. If you're a counter trend trader, you want to only be trading
on the dist have a midflow. Yeah, you correct. Even though both are
classified as midflow themselves. So again, I'm trying to
like instill the importance of us having the necessary language
to describe prices
and another thing
you know
there's a completely different
dynamic in trading
in its point in liquidity
in the level
compared to waiting
for price to come
compared to taking the retest
yeah
because on the retest
we need the liquidity
to be strong
whereas taking the trade
at the exhaustion
I don't need to sell
liquidity to be strong
I just need to fucking
bare weakness on the bids
to get it
I just need
super super thin by weakness so it doesn't take a strong level to push price down compared to
an apex meter which requires much much thicker sell liquidity to be present you're in a bit
managing position as well if you catch that that first bit exactly so how would we be able to
differentiate between the two if we didn't have the basic language to describe it is kind of a point
in other words if this is more favorable to take a trade at the point of exhaustion then we could
draw and make an inference that the more accurately we can describe price and
textualize price the more accurately we can identify favorable combinations of
price behaviors and features that lead to consistency and like you know that are
exploitable price behaviors that are exploitable versus price behaviors that are less
disposable that are less favorable yeah in other words the whole point is to here is to find
a combination of price features parameters price behaviors a combination of them
that consistently yield responses and give us edge, basically.
So, yeah, we're looking at the components of price that we need to assess,
or the key metrics in price that we need to assess,
which I would broadly define as volatility, state of liquidity,
which is directly related to volatility, because the principle is volatility
is a function of available liquidity
and we need to assess
the price swings as well, the price swing stages
which are the visual formations,
the visual structures as a result of
equity
how price moves. Exactly.
So there are three main things
we need to assess. Under these two
falls price delivery and how price is moving.
Under price ring before
the price rate stage and they're
closely related as we just discussed
in midflow, right?
These are going to be the main
things we're trying to assess and breaking the price swing structure down into
into actual structures and then it's a stage of so and then given each of those
three stages characteristics so mid-flow characteristics we discussed apex
characteristics are successful apex based on visual examples over and over again
the first pick-up should hold if the character is if the effect is strong the
The shelf should fail to push the lows, d-da-da-da-da, right?
Ideally, in the strongest of Apex's Paisol have pushed through Shelf in the first goal,
the Apex retest, it can have a, it can be,
typically shouldn't even reach that far back into the pickup.
If the Bile could, it is super, super strong.
But then, here we're talking about variations of Apex,
just the same way as variations of mid-flow.
The broader characteristics are the same.
The low holds, the retest holds, the shelf fails to push the new lows,
we then push through the shelf and hopefully stabilise above it
before we shift into abolishment block.
So given each of those stages characteristics,
we can then use those characteristics.
If you consistently track priceings over and over and over again,
you will eventually use the characteristic
to assess the changes in the environment anyway.
So if price is here, we just flip shelves.
Now you suddenly start to see Price do this quite early on.
earlier on here he was anticipating
and it's changing the bullish midflow
but now the visual characteristics that you
that are you know
that are the characteristics of the flow
that are the components of midflow
you're seeing it happen in lifetime
fractal price swings
the characteristics of midflow
are all confirming to you
what price is doing
and we know and bullish midflow that the last buy
should hold so it's reasonable
to say that if buyers are strong
the last base should continue to hold
you get it
if this is residual liquidity
on the left
which is again a component
of price swings
it's a feature of price swings
because residual liquidity
is left over thin liquidity
that was thinly traded
of a particular swing
then these high shouldn't have
enough fuel in them
to push past the last inch
you get it
it should just be just
extension fills
because the move
into the residual liquidity
was quite thin at the time
so the whole point is here the language that I'm going through with and and you know subliminally
I'm kind of reaffirming the significance of the pricing stages and whatnot is you know it's profound
significant you need it need it to a high degree of like we need it allows us it allows us to see
the market on a granular level the idea is the the the information that we can extract
from that quite a little view is so significant
that we can make more informed decisions
about where prices are going to go next than
anybody else. That is on
our level anyway. Because me and you
we just can't compete with HFTs in it.
There's no way it was to
transact on the level. I didn't even
open this driving. Yeah, the most
I got of it was from the
apex in the shelves. It was
a lot of stuff that
I really didn't know.
Yes, the big shelf's more shelf.
Yeah, the consolidation.
Apex. I think one time
actually, I can't remember how many sessions ago
this was, but you did show me a
consolidation Apex and you said
we'll discuss why
this isn't as favourable.
I think it was stair stepping.
So it was an apex
that was doing this
back into it? Yeah,
yeah, exactly.
Yeah, it's basically
in the stronger Apexes,
you're typically going to have
so much weakness in the shelf
combined with so much strength
on the opposite side of the market
that the shelf
liquidity doesn't even have to reach that
price doesn't even have to reach that far up
to find sellers they're willing to snap here
willing to transact to that level
and ultimately absorb the shelf and push through
whereas in the
the different type of apex
price ultimately
absorbs whatever sell liquidity was here
goes and grabs all of it
So one thing to validate or to discuss and to introduce you to is that a liquidity base is simply an area where price was stable and trade was being facilitated and then you typically have a surge out from it.
It can be quite a slow surge.
It doesn't have to pop out of it.
It can actually grind out of it like this.
But in either case, the liquidity state shifts, as you can imagine here.
One side is weaker, the cell of liquidity is thinner and is drawing away,
and the buy volume is chasing after it.
You typically have left behind a pool of liquidity that wants to transact and trade.
Is that the level that you took from today's trade?
Yeah, yeah.
This is a fractal core.
It's a fractal apex.
But the point I'm making here is that all types of liquidity bases,
whether it's a fractal core, whether it's a residual liquidity base,
they have some form of liquidity in them
and there's three sides to it
there's a top, a middle and a bottom
right
if you have a base and price reaches to the bottom
of it is cleared out all the liquidity there can be
expected to have gone yeah
the only remaining liquidity would be in the last
area that grabbed it
that picked up the liquidity
be strong
we wouldn't expect it to be strong
So if you have an apex
which just picked up an area of cell
liquidity, I pick up again
fills some cell limit orders
there. In the strong apexes
we can expect the cell limit orders
to actually move down and to here and hold price
down. Yeah. But if
price ends up absorbing all of
the liquidity and grabbing the top side of that
fractal liquidity base,
that fractal pickup,
we actually call the
we actually call the pickup
of a base that OPE,
the original pick-up
so this is the original
pick-up of this level
if price then comes and
in the way it leaves that level
if it absorbs all of that liquidity there
we can anticipate
that on return to that level
there shouldn't be enough there to actually
power another move
even if it does that move will likely be weak
and price will ultimately move through it
yeah because that ends up being like the pickup
of the pickup doesn't it
yeah it's picked up an area that's already been picked
up and we're just draining the last bit of liquidity left everything.
So the point I'm making is the more we test the level, as everybody knows, it gets weaker.
But here we're looking at from a finite quantitative point of view, the liquidity is being drained.
And if an apex forms in this way, we're grabbed all the liquidity on the way out anyway,
on return to that level, we typically are going to see price move through it.
Not a straight line, but any response off there will usually be weak and price will end up moving through it anyway.
So the variation of the apex definitely matters.
But a consolidation apex is just that point of a price run
where previously in the bullish midflow, the apex is,
well, the shelf liquidity was so much so that I pushed through to new highs.
But at an apex, the shelf liquidity hasn't got enough momentum,
enough punching power, enough fuel to move through.
And actually typically, they'll be opposing strength on the opposite side of the market as well.
think about it this way during bullish midflow price puts in this high of a residual level of opposing cell liquidity because of exhaustion in the up move yeah in a consolidation apex you'll typically see weakness in the up move and cell strength on the on the cell liquidity as well i see a core area of cell liquidity
do you get it yeah there's a combination of weakness and strength and that's typically going to have enough fuel to power through and then considering this is holding the
bulk of the momentum liquidity on an automated execution basis and how liquidity is filtered
in for large orders, when price does push through the shelf, we typically see a shift occur
where bi-liquity can start to withdraw, right? So if bi-liquity is weaker past the shelf,
we will typically see the bearish mid-flow take place. So past the shelf is like a change,
it's a threshold where liquidity can shift and change. We haven't seen it here.
we saw sell liquidity hold price down
sell liquidity hold price down
we broke the shelf
we tested the apex
and then once we finally stabilised all the apex
above the shelf sorry
we saw a change in the state of liquidity
yeah because if the move
was still going to continue
it would respect the last
well yeah the last inventory
what the move down
yeah yeah yeah
now if you look at it this way
yeah we this is the last inventory
that pushed price down we broke it early
the morning, popped through, didn't really hit a good level.
On a minute scale anyway, on a microscale, it didn't really hit a good level, but still
price was able to push through to the weaker side.
There was weakness in sell liquidity here because it was washed.
And then that moved down, didn't have enough in isolation, that moved down, dried off,
price flipped its shelf, and it had to reach past it to find the next area of liquidity.
Do you get it?
So all the cell limit orders here
Not all, but the majority of it was weak and drained
Once this fractal run dry it off
It didn't take that much volume
To push price back off
To push price through the thinner area
Reaching for the thicker area
Which is the next area here
And the same thing applies in this move down
Actually look at the responses
Weak response, weak response, weak response
Because this low here was grabbed, grabbed, grabbed, grabbed
And then moved out
It's all drained and washed
so on the way down
and also that move up
is super super thin
didn't leave much liquidity
behind it's residual
here's your shelf
the shelf couldn't hold price up
once we push through the shelf
change in the state of liquidity
trying to find bids
trying to find bids trying to find bids
the sellers dried off there
not because there's a huge amount of bids
but the cell got weaker
and then obviously we shot through
and finally reached the level
if you actually
look at
if you saw this live
you would have seen the ticking
here price just went parabolic in his tick
frequency reaching for the level
reaching for the level stretching out
that's the condition I'm looking to trade under
the tick frequency increases
was this the
smallest scale that you viewed this move on
or did you go down to the tick chart as well
no when I took the entry I was on the one minute
I was on the one minute the only
time I would need to look at the tick
chart is like a move like this
let's say I wanted to assess
if there's any levels inside of it can you see
the levels not that distinctively
anyway you can't see it there there may be
a level there there's possibly a level there
there there's possibly level there but
because it's such a thin move on the one minute
I can't see much in there so I need to zoom in
how we can see more granularity
yeah
this move can't see foothole inside of it
even on the 20 tick chart
so if I wanted to look inside of it
doesn't mean I do if I did
I would need a closer view.
Yeah, okay.
Just like a zoom, zooming function.
One thing that is a constant,
as you can see, there's more granularity.
Actually, see stability, surge, drawback in, stability.
You know, in that highly inefficient move,
there's midflow characteristics inside of it.
The midflow is the building block of that inefficiency,
the imbalance.
But, yeah, what you will find is that for timing of trades,
let's say, you know, like this is a five-minute rule,
not even if it's a one minute price room on here because one minute is such a small scale we you know basically on the one minute you basically see that price isn't always this flash inefficient exhaustion type right for the most part it's quite stable even under one minute even though this whole move is inefficient broadly speaking not a lot of buying was for not a lot of buy liquidity was present here so not a lot of sell trades were facilitated yeah it was stretched out thin the whole movement
might have had a huge volume transaction in it,
a huge order filled,
but at each individual level,
not huge by liquidity,
was there for the sellers to match with.
But in terms of time in the trade,
I would only see that prices become super, super thin
and inefficient on the lower time frame.
I would not see that on a higher time frame.
So in terms of timing trades
and looking for that exhaustion at the end of a price run,
we need the lower time frame as well.
So we needed to get a view inside of things
we can't see inside of.
We need the lower time frame for that.
still can't see what's in that
in this move here
yeah that you know that
thing you got marked down
exactly that's why we need a lower time frame
in this instance
but here we can see plenty
you know yeah
so it just depends on how inefficient
that run it in and of itself is
we also need a lower time frame for timing
of the trade now
you know like my level here
is a fractal core
it's a fractal apex
we have this area
of washed liquidity
and we know that price goes
at less liquid side
it goes to the less liquid side
and we know volatility
is a function of available liquidity
in volatile price moves
we know that there's little transactions
being facilitated
or little trade being facilitated
at each individual level
price stretches out
becomes inefficient
that's the effect of the volatility
the volatility is induced
by market structure
or market depth dynamics
to buy liquidity disappears
or whatnot, whatnot. But in either case, the trade model that I could extract from this
or trade parameters that could extract from this is a very consistent one. Whenever you have
a watch level, the price reaches past it, it almost always draws back in. So extension, get it filled.
Extensions get filled. That's one of the price behaviors I'm exploiting. With specific,
the specific parameters inside of it is this core bioliquity of a fractal,
on a fractal yeah there's a fractal apex there the core of it with no core liquidity strong there's a highly inefficient move there which is at this point quite easily the parabolic phase of this run yeah we ran we ran we ran we broke bed flow and then we we distinctively broke midflow again and then we here we've had quite a big shot yeah so at this point in time this would be the big shelf we'll see there's a small
shelf there, then there's a medium fucking shelf there, right?
And we know there's weaknesses to sell liquidity in this price room.
So what the specific trade would be extension into core liquidity in the parabolic phase
or after a break of midflow of a H1 price swing.
They're the three main components of this trade.
And if we try to identify this exact condition,
you won't get that frequently basically
it was too good of a trade basically
like this one we have a washed liquidity here again
it's an extension again
but this isn't a core
this is residual liquidity
slightly different from this hitting a core base
not
those two could have drastically different outcomes
over a thousand samples
yeah
this one would be more favourable
I can identify that
because we you know we're breaking price down
into these necessary compartments and categories
so we can differentiate between
this trade which is quite similar to this trade
but this one's more favourable because of the level it hit.
Again, we need that granularity.
We need that framework to be able to assess price
and give it locations to assess types of levels,
give levels locations,
differentiate between good and bad levels, etc.
I would clearly say that this has a lower expectancy
of outcome
compared to a core area of liquidity that this hit you follow me yeah was that was that core area
of liquidity on like the h1 or something because i know i know you got the fractal of it but no no no no it's
the core area of this i should stop saying core it's a fractal apex okay it's a fractal apex it's not a core
it's actually technically residual of this h1 price rate but it's a fractal apex okay yeah i was
just asking just because on your the videos that are in the drive and stuff you love like your
your H1 levels and choosing the fractal
from the inside of them
yeah because the principle
that applies here is high time frame pulls more
liquidity more lick
more liquidity means
a greater certainty of you know weakness
failing to put a thin move failing to push
through it you get it yeah
so a high time frame level spent more time
building up there so it leaves more liquidity behind
when a thin move comes into it
there's a greater likelihood of response
compared to a one minute level
then when price returns
turns to a price didn't spend that long there building up liquidity so there's relative to the
size of the response there's a lower likelihood of price responding in a huge way of a one minute
level that makes sense so again if we didn't differentiate between the timeframes of the level
the quality of the like the observations we make wouldn't be as good i keep going back to this
here what we the purpose of me identified those three main components
is if I told you to go identify those exact conditions over and over again,
you could possibly build a trade model, a trade model with specific parameters and rules
that you've identified that work over and over again, that you validated, which could form
a model of trading that works consistently of a large sample that will guarantee make you
money. If you didn't have a way to assess washed areas or a way to assess price delivery,
if we never focused on that we might be able to identify this price behavior still you know we can
still see that price fills extensions but then how do you differentiate between this extension and that
extension this one is so much more favorable than that one because this hits a core area of liquidity
can you see just add in that extra bit of information can be the difference between a good
and a bad trade in both instances by the way they worked I'm saying over a big sample this will
work more frequently and as it stands right now this is open to running 60 pips
quite late in the day though quite late in the day so it wouldn't be surprised
the price is stabilized overnight and then the dynamic changes you know because the volume
will stabilize overnight the liquidity will lighten up as well so early in the morning when
the volume surge comes through it could quite easily because there's this thin liquidity in the
books it could quite easily end up reaching past it but if this happened
at 2 p.m. today or 9 a.m. today, I'd be holding on to this trade likely as well with
might, probably be adding to it as well. But if you look at another way of validating price
behaviours, which, you know, here's a fractal run, price returned back to the origin,
we broke midflow here, came relatively inefficient at the lows, and we've had quite a nice
response. So even on a granular level, on the fractal price, we've seen the same behaviours repeat
over and over again. These are residual levels. Prices, weak response of residual levels and
continuing through. Buy basis for now holding. This has had a quite deep test, so that's washed.
We retested the wash level again. Then we popped through. We actually didn't hit a great level,
but here's shelf of this up move, here's the breakout accumulation, here's the top side, which is
technically washed. No, it won't be a surprise if price extended up and there and sold off.
or price broke mid-flow
extend up and they unsold off
it could do that
if you're just viewing this in isolation
now let's contextualize this
let's see how this fits in the broader context
well we've just had a five-minute shell flip here
or break of shelf here
not flipped here but break
we know that this
hit residual liquidity
after breaking the H-1 higher time
for embrace mid-flow and this is likely
and possibly the parabolic phase
so we are possibly in this stage
here. Break amid flow, surge
and now drawing back in.
Do you get it? Yeah.
Would you expect
sell liquidity in this leg to be strong?
No, not up until the core base.
I mean, up until, yeah, the origin.
I would make the, you know, okay, cool.
So the strongest
liquidity in here would likely be
at the origin. But broadly speaking,
there can be reactions
off the residual liquidity, but
you wouldn't really expect it to have
strong ones.
And I wouldn't expect this to be strong either
because this has already drained
that higher time frame area of saliquity anyway.
You get it because it broke the midflop.
So if we quickly go clone this chart.
We were in Burrish midflow,
bearish midflow, we broke, distinctively broke
and had a parabolic phase.
After the parabolic phase,
we can expect an apex formation,
a shell flip and a reversal.
Then back into bullish midflow.
So we would actually expect this to be weak
based off the context.
It's not guaranteed to be weak
just because it's probable
It doesn't mean it's guaranteed
We need to see price continuously reflect the weakness
So we can maintain our bias
If price starts to show self-strength
You know up here and I'm long
For example, it's the end of the day
I'm long and prices broke mid-flow
And it pops through
There's a high, high likelihood
I'll be caught in my trade
Or scaling some profit off
Because of the weakness in this fractal run
If I was long still, do you get it?
Yeah. So price should continue
the more favourable version here would be
if Price maintained bullish mid-flow
surged through,
then I might be more willing to accept
Price drawing back against me.
Where's the big shelf in that move?
Yeah.
Oh, this whole move?
No, no, yeah.
Just that move there.
Which one?
Yeah, you've already...
Yeah, the whole move.
Yeah, that one there.
Yeah, that's the big show.
You look at it.
one, sell off, sell off, sell off.
This is a more distinct
to break amid flow and this is the last
image of the shelf, right?
So that's possible as well and this is
all washed and weak.
So yeah,
what was I saying?
So, okay, yeah, what I said is
if you review this in isolation, we could
infer or anticipate that it's a strong
and good area of sell equity because it's a fractal
VA, right, inside of
the core area. But when you
give it context, when you give
this fractal swing
location, we could quickly realize
that it's hitting, first of all, residual
equity. Yeah.
Residious weak.
Yeah, so residuals weak.
But then this whole run itself
is in the parabolic phase of a leg.
So break in midflow, parabolic
phase, and we typically don't see the parabolic
leg be a leg of significance.
In other words, what I mean is
that doesn't typically push to new lows.
We actually see a reversal and a shift
after the parabolic leg.
Yeah.
We are currently around here.
So to expect one of these fractal apexes to provide a nice apex retest, for example,
does it make that much sense of them?
Do you get it?
To expect the sell liquidity here to be strong wouldn't be, in my opinion, a positive expectancy trade.
It wouldn't be a viable trade to take an actual trader.
I would actually expect weak responses of sell liquidity here and buyers to continue through.
simply just using the prize swing stages as a guidance of certain expectations for what I should do.
Not setting, making predictions, but just certain expectations of what price should do.
If this is a successful swing, we know swings occur frequently over and over again,
we take that repeating swing structure and break it down into stages.
We know that after the sideways pop, sideways pop stage, price typically tends to draw back in form apex and shift higher.
Then why would you be bearish here?
Yeah, it doesn't make sense
Number one, it doesn't make sense
If you can find evidence
Let's say based off higher time frame
That sellers should be strong here and continue lower
Maybe the biliquity super super weak
Higher timeframes suggest bearishness etc
Then there's merit for it
But you need to build that merit
Based of experience and using fractal
Using timeframes
Which is the next next level
You will do it
But as of right now
Just simply using price swing stages
to set guidance for what is likely to happen,
not guaranteed likely to happen,
it wouldn't make sense to actually look for short responses here.
And over two,
we could actually start to look at how.
Price builds up to the level.
Yeah, what variations in routes price could take
based of experience.
You know, you will be posed with the shell flips.
And whilst the shell flips are forming,
there's many different variations of how it could unfold.
it could reach back down here and pop
it could just drive higher
I've actually seen like shell flips
like breaking the shelf going into nothing
and then going up even higher
creating new highs
yeah yeah
as in like
price break shelf and then continues
yeah yeah yeah likely this hit
nothing shit liquidity
that would be class as a break amid flow
rather than a material
shell
rather than a material apex.
That's another actually quite an important point.
When price does break mid-flow,
before it continues to new highs,
it looks like an apex anyway.
Yeah, it does.
So it's important that you don't set rigid expectations
for what price you should do.
You don't have rigid expectations
that every single time price breaks shelf
that you're going to go bearish
because,
based off simple experience
you've already told me that
there's instances where price goes to new highs
now you have two possible outcomes
a broader reference point
of experience for what price
could do in this particular stage
when it breaks mid-flow
in other words
you now have a more accurate
understanding of what price might do in that particular stage
compared to the person who has strict
rule-based rigid expectations
for one price has to do when a break shelf.
Based of simple Bayesian influence,
based of simple observations over time,
you have a reference point mentally
of what a shell flip means,
or break a shelf means,
based of experience,
you will broaden that reference point.
This will include different variations,
different types of variations of apexes.
You will broaden to ways apexes can fail
it will actually also include
the types of level the apex
you know the high hit before it broke shelf
the type of level it hit
and whether that has it influence on whether
the high fails or price continues
yeah price delivery moving to a level
no no so if this is a residual level
and then price breaks shelf
I wouldn't actually be expecting the height to hold
because it's a residual level
but then when it's a
like this, this low, actually
hits a good level, a core level
this higher
likelihood of the high holding
because there's more stronger sell liquidity there
or buy liquidity in this instance.
Now I also said to you,
if prices in bullish midflow
and it has not yet broke bullish midflow
and then we break midflow,
do you expect this retest to hold?
No.
Why?
Because, well, usually after this
comes the...
Exactly.
Sideways part and then, yeah.
So depending on where the break of shelf comes in,
we can set realistic expectations for whether this,
because this could in theory,
and sometimes will turn into a bearish shell flip and shift,
but probabilistically no,
because it hasn't done a sideways pop.
Also, when Price does break the shelf,
break midflare for the first time, break the shelf,
it's typically going to hit residual level of liquidity,
not a strong area of liquidity.
that will also help me form
or set relative expectation
of whether I expect this to reverse
or continue higher.
Can you see how adding variables
can help us assess
whether price will continue higher or not?
There'll be clear,
clear distinct differences
in between the types of levels price
actually flips and reverses off
and the time it does it as well.
It'll be often sideways pop
most often compared to the
the high that pushed through the mid-flow,
the shelf that broke mid-flow,
failing and price continuing to new highs.
So it's critical that we are consistently identifying
or extracting all the necessary information from price
to make these more informed decisions.
Yeah, there was a lot of thought that actually went into this trade.
You would think so, but no, I'll just track it all day.
I was waiting for this.
You would think, yeah?
But it's so autonomous now.
it's so like intuitive based
all I have to do is channeled their intuition
I have to make sure that I follow a process
the process is channeling
like the things I'm focusing on
rather than me sitting there and saying
okay I'm building this trade idea
these are the cases for it
these are the cases against it I don't even do that
oh yeah no no I know I know now you don't think like that
I'm just saying that to me it seems like
yeah yeah
I can imagine
but
went into it
and stuff
the benefit
of consistently
interacting
the price
over a big span
of time
is internalization
you build
something called
second level
information
things like
it basically
it's intuition
yeah
so you notice
the exact
nature of
price moves
the types
of the exact
nature of levels
the exact
nature of the
price swing
let's say
stage in
environment
which consistently
result in
certain types
of occurrences
over another
so you
recognize it quickly and in this instance it was quite clear to me that I should be
waiting for this good level rather than the shit level it was clear to me that under
this environment I would be taking this I should place a limit order here
etc etc you get it yeah so yeah so one thing that you're going to be
basically doing depending on how well you do it will directly influence your
conviction this intuitive feeling I'm talking about how well you differentiate between
winners and losers, is exercising without having live exposure.
Because when you're exercising without live exposure,
you're there to extract as much information as you can about all forms of outcomes,
negative outcomes, positive outcomes.
So if you take a trade here and it fails,
because you have, you know, you take a potential trade here and you fails,
because you have no exposure on the line,
you are better positioned to identify all the reasons for why this trade didn't work,
the relevant features that mark,
the relevant information that matters,
i.e.
residual liquidity is weak.
High time frame,
sellers are weak.
This is a recent bullish shell flip.
Why are you going short, basically?
You know, the shell flip alone,
price pushing past the shelf alone
is telling us sellers a week in this price run.
So why the fuck are you going short
on a retest of a high
that hit a weak area in the first place?
What merit have you got to say
that there's enough sell equity here
to absorb the recent strength
that price is showing and push
lower. Do you get it?
You actually said this in your process video
actually. You have to build like a positive
well you have to like track price
what you're looking at and build a positive
expectancy. Identify
yeah identify which behaviours have a positive
expectancy and which behaviours
have a negative expectancy. You cannot
do that if you have live money on the line
because if I put a live trade on here
I'm directly emotionally engaged with it
and first of all it's likely that at this point
if you're doing it prematurely trading live
you don't have a definable edge
you can't differentiate between what's positive expectancy
and what's not
so you'll have periods where the market goes your way
sometimes you'll have periods of the market
doesn't go your way
and in the instances not going your way
you are not extracting information
from market anymore
you're there most usually if you're a normal human being
most usually just reeling off that loss you just made
looking for the next move
in other words like just because this lost
you will trade this level in a way where it has to work
if you took an entry here rather than
observing if the response is favourable
every single tick that price
you know that that unfolds
will have to be favorable for you
rather than you being open-minded
about what's possible.
Yeah, that's true.
So your frame of thinking
typically is inappropriate
when you're trading live
with live exposure when you exercise it
because exercising is not looking to take
a thousand winning trades in a day
or a hundred winning trades in a day.
It's about taking all types of trades
under all variations of price swing,
stages, face of liquidity, volatility.
So you can assess
if that particular combination of trade,
components and parameters
have a positive expectancy or not
that's why I just talked about
the three components of this trade
how they're different from this trade
although they're quite similar both are extensions
but this one has more
favourable components involved with it
so they're leveled strong the moves weak
and it's at the end hopefully have a price
swing if that makes sense
you know that first dry off
on the other move
yeah
it doesn't look like it actually went into anything
it just seems that just because it was an inefficient move
that it just drove.
It was so weak.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So this didn't hit a fucking liquidity base.
Yeah.
That's an entirely different dynamic compared to taking the trade in a liquidity base.
That's a core liquidity base, etc.
These two, even though in this instance they both responded,
these two will have a massively different expectancy over the long run.
Yeah.
You have to, when you're exercising,
in engage both types of trades
but that engagement
doesn't matter if you're not
differentiating between the parameters
of this trade and this trade here
to get it
if you didn't classify this trade as
not hitting a level
and if you didn't classify this trade
as hitting a level
if all we looked at is both moves
are inefficient and both moves are extensions
you know if we ignored
that this did the hit a level and this did
then this seems to be the exact same trade
you get it
both are extensions both were inefficient
then there must be the same trade
but the more relevant information we extract them out here
we come to realize that this is actually a residual level
and it's a residual area with no fucking level inside of it
whereas this here an actual fractal apex
etc you get it
so the quality of the the exercises that
you are going to take depends on how well
you're contextualizing price.
You're not there.
In other words, you can't
contextualize price as of right now.
You're going to have to go through that process
of tracking live prices,
building your ability to contextualize it.
When you're tracking it as well,
you're going to be using the CPS framework
to try and set expectations for what price
you do next. What should price do here
if this is a successful spriced swing? Just this one here.
Well, they should fucking flip the shelf
and go to bullishment flow, no?
Also, then if that's the case,
If this is a successful price swing,
we should ideally see the buy-based hold.
It doesn't have to, buy-based hold,
and the sell areas of liquidity to not hold.
At least in this immediate location right now,
I would want to see these apexes not hold
and the bids to start pushing through
and a fractal mid-flow to take place here.
Yeah, it looks good at the moment
because it's pushed through the shelf.
Yeah, it's pushed through the shelf,
and then it hasn't created no new lows.
It's created a higher higher.
but think about it, this could quite easily draw all the way back down here
and then run to the upside.
Would you expect that?
This is still a valid apex if it does.
Would that, you know, if I told you to track this now and tell me what's going to happen,
would you come up with the appropriate variations of what price might do,
just simply using CPS?
And the answer is no, you're going to be wrong.
Your expectation of what price is going to do next,
my expectation of what price is going to do next is almost certainly going to
to be wrong over the long row if you did it a thousand times try to predict the future a thousand
times you're going to be wrong yeah but what will happen is you will set an expectations for what
price should do and it will do it in a slightly different way than you expected which will broaden your
your reference point of understanding of what's possible yeah it makes you more open-minded about
what price can do and the right way to approach it it will move you away from having strict
rigid expectations for yeah price has to go up here and has to do it now rather it will be
a more of a probability focused approach what does price need to do for this area to remain
favourable or for this play of price running to the upside and flipping the shelf to remain
favourable well the key key component would be the low should hold yeah low should hold and then
buy bases also hold eventually after the shelf flip yeah you get it so you get it so
So because I understand there's multiple variations
for how price can reach this destination
if the bid so strong on the sellers a week,
I look for the characteristics
which maintain the likelihood and the favorability of the happening
compared to, compared to me saying,
yeah, they should move up here, then down there,
then Donald Trump's mom should,
you get it like, I'm not going to set rigid expectations
because you're very, you're exposing yourself to be wrong.
when I tell you to track price
I'm kind of tricking you into
setting rigid expectations
you get it
you're going to feel the burn of being wrong about
what price should do next
you're going to be wrong
there will be uncertainty by what price does next
we'll be starting to do that in the next
next like one or two sessions
but as of right now
the task will be
every single day that you can
every single minute of the day that you can
because the markets will stop moving
sorry, Monday to Friday,
it should be to identify
as many swings as you can.
And really, rather than building...
On any time frame or...
Any time frame, historical charts,
look at different variations of price swings,
different time frame price swings,
just to validate that these swings exist.
And don't just look at them,
look at like, when did this break-knit flow?
How often, you know, did this break-met flow?
How often did the biggest flow?
The different variations of apexes,
the different variations of shelf flips,
look at this shell flip it got beneath it and it retested it three times yeah this shell flip
it fucking didn't even retest it bro it just it tests the top side of it came in for apex retest
and then broke through it rather than retesting it you get it yeah there's different variations
the apex conform the shelves conform the brakes in the flow conform I just want you to get
and start building a visual mental reference a sample set in your brain through engaged
interactive exercises but the task is this you need to build a sample set 10 15 price swings that
you like down and up price swings on different time frames just just note to the variations and
differences you don't want me to go like proper into detail about the stuff proper into it because
I would assume you understand anyway what you're doing here is you're you're validating that
the price swings exist visually and on a on a subconscious
the scale, you're building your ability
to see them on minute details and price swings
that may or may not
be significant to you. So on all
of the swings, I want you to know when the shelf
broke for the first time
or the sideways, the pops,
all the swing stages as best
you can. You know,
if this midflow broke midflow
early, then circle there and write it
down. Yeah. Do you get it?
Yeah. But you don't have to go
mud, my detail. And do swings
in isolation. Don't do
swing after swing after swing on one chart
pick up one swing that's good to you
and then do that and then pick one swing
that's a bit less clear and do that
you get it
yeah that's fine 10 15
a sample set once you get that done next session
would be basically just moving on to like doing
tracking life prices the dynamics of using CPS
to set expectations
like I said I'm going to put you in a position
where you're going to be wrong you're going to set strict
expectations for what price should do
and as long as you maintain focus
and you engage,
that will broaden your reference point
on what price can do
in every single stage.
So prices in an apex
like it is right now,
this could actually fail.
You get it?
It's got actually fail.
If over, let's say,
500 examples of apex failures,
there's going to be quite similar characteristics
in how the apex has failed
in all of them.
Do you get it?
They'll also likely be
other conditions
or other components that are relative
to why this apex is more likely to fail.
So like this one, it hit residual liquidity.
You get it?
Maybe that increases the likelihood of the apex not working.
Or decreases the likelihood of the apex working
when it hits residual liquidity.
Maybe when prices in bearish midflow
and it hasn't broke midflow yet
and then it responds off the next level,
maybe that also decreases the likelihood of the apex reversal.
Do you get it?
So you'll be like building a side.
sample to have information mentally regarding that.
We'll discuss that next session.
It's called,
basically second available information, yeah?
We need to discuss that quickly.
Also, I'm going to give you next session a template
on the four different variations of apexes,
the main ones at least,
what they look like, something like that.
There's four main ones,
and then I'm going to get you to find them,
and then I'm going to discuss with you
the exact dynamics around
managing an apex when I take
entry. If I go along
here, what am I looking for?
When am I going to cut the trade? The different
options I have to manage the trade.
And then I'm going to introduce you to the exercise and
process. You've already done, you're already doing
step one now, which is identifying
swings and building your ability to see the swing
features. The second
step is centred around you being able to
track price. So using
CPS to set expectations for what price
you do, but avoiding
set and rigid expectations,
broadening your understanding of what price can do
in each individual stage,
so where you can do it mid-flow,
how it can fairly mid-flow,
how it can be a successful mid-flow,
based on your experiences,
you'll make small adjustments in your mindset
on what's possible and what's not,
and what's the right way to think,
what's the wrong way to think,
avoid mental conflicts, basically.
Just get used to tracking something as dynamic.
If something's always changing,
you can't always have, if something's always changing,
it's inappropriate to have rigid expectation, basically.
I just want you to get used to that.
That takes away a significant amount of, let's say, adverse response to uncertainty.
You actually start to embrace uncertainty.
There's no way around it.
We don't know what's going to happen next.
So you actually come up with measures and solutions to combat randomness and uncertainty.
Things like considering multiple outcomes, tracking price closely for subtle changes in price.
if you didn't track it how would you know when it's changed
you don't want to see it we want to be the first to see the changes
yeah also by tracking it you can tell when
it's not going your way and you can cut it before an actual loss as well
exactly so that that is directly one yeah
you're going to be the first one to see the changes etc so
but bear in mind before you have an adequate level of
let's say mental reference point to put to consider multiple outcomes
accurately, you're going to consider
outcomes that are completely out of whack and wrong.
And when you're tracking price, for you to identify
what's favour or what's not, to accurately
identify when to cut the trade or not,
you're going to have made hundreds and
maybe thousands of decisions that were the wrong thing
to do before you realise
what the right thing to do is. Obviously,
I'm going to be there to tell you what you should and shouldn't do,
but I bet you will listen, a good
majority of the times until you finally make the
realization of this is why that motherfucker was saying
that it's just the way this thing works and and none of this will work if you start to trade
live because you had three bear in mind i do not profit of making you not trade live
once your 24 sessions are over you can come back to me for advice but that's it like my time is
done yeah of course so i won't i won't profit off most people will like tell you don't trade live
or do this or do that just to long it out and continue you're not a subscriber you're not
paying me on a rolling subscription.
So I have no interest,
monetary at least, monetarily at least,
to keeping you on
not trading life.
But I'm always talking from a
no, you're from
the point of view of progression.
The quality, yeah, and you will not
progress past the appropriate
levels or two appropriate
levels if you had a period
of, let's say, three weeks where the price environment
was perfect and you got responsiveness.
Because the data environment
changes you're fucked yeah you know you'll be lucky to get three weeks by the way but it can happen
it has happened in the past where someone has had a perfect environment for three weeks they've tried
to start trading live then they come back to me now oh it's not working anymore i'm like you're a
fucking idiot so so in that week after he just went to yeah it just went left where went west
but it happens and depending on how well you do the initial stage i might even get you to trade live
just for you to experience the difference
there's been one student where I've actually told
you should go fucking life
just so you experience what it's really like
making decisions
because he was doing everything really well
in the exercising
then he came back to me
two, three weeks later
I was like yo it's all different
I told him to go back to training
exercising
focusing on what yeah so
think about it
building enough experiences to consider outcomes correctly
building enough experiences to
shift your mindset
appropriately for the dynamic
the randomness of markets, dynamic probabilities, etc.
It has to be done in a vacuum.
Vacuum is like you're being protected
from the real risk of losing or making money.
Only once you've built that conviction,
that deep ingrained, burnt,
you know, once those memories and those skills
and the intuition is burnt into your psyche,
once it's internalized,
once you've built a trade model
that has positive expectancy,
only then
you're best prepared to cross over that threshold
of taking small live trades
and if I'm realistic with you, what day is it now?
17th, 90th of November
you'll be lucky to have live success
you'll be trading life hopefully by that point
with a small account, I'm talking 50 quid, 100 quid
you'll be lucky
God more would have blessed you
if you by 19th and November next year
or cake in it.
But you might be able,
think about it this way as well,
I am one normal person.
Yeah.
I'm just me with my limited capacity
and blessings or whatnot.
You might be totally different.
You would only know that
if you put in the necessary work.
You get it.
You can only expose yourself
to the blessing to know whether you,
like you might be that guy
that can do it within six months,
you just connect to it,
you pick it up,
you put in enough work.
You might be that guy.
But the way
I tell everyone that you'd be lucky within a year
that would take you a good 18 months
to internalize all the different types of environments.
Just look at it this way.
You've had one big three-month period
of stable, efficient prices.
You think that, you know,
why if you had a flash crash tomorrow?
Do you understand what I'm trying to say?
That risk of that shift in the state of liquidity,
that volatility change can be the difference
between, you know, like you could have a long position
with a stop-loss.
In the right, flash crash environment,
that stop-plus could get filled down here.
you can lose your whole account in a single flash crash
plus negative as well
plus negative yeah so
there's so many possible outcomes that can occur
and things and that like
a single three month period of exercising isn't enough
you have to expose yourself to the market dynamics
over a big big sample
and make a process appropriate for that
do you get it
what kind of sample size are you talking like if you put a number on it
what do you mean samples as well
like say collected collected samples or
or experiences
interactions with the market
yeah like interactions
of the market
because I mean
with the CPS
you're not looking to
trade everything
are you you're looking to
in your exercises you are
yeah in your exercise
but I mean like
after that
you just look for
like how you do
like midflow or something
you just want to
be honest of you
my plan is just trade
at the thinest point
of exhaustion
at good areas of liquidity
I will only trade
midflow
if it's like
a H1 midflow
like this
I won't be trading
this 5 minute flow here.
You get it?
Yeah.
So how many experiences do you need?
Let's just say in an hour, if you're directly ignoring that your productivity dies down after like four hour period.
Ignoring, yeah?
Yeah.
In a single hour period on a one minute chart, you could probably collect about 10 to 15 good experiences.
Right?
but then eventually you're going to have to include context
because if I just view this on the one minute
devoid of any context we know there's a risk
that this could shift into volishment flow
and if that started to expand then
I should have what was it that I missed
on the one minute that caused this to expand
maybe that information it's very likely
the higher type of information would have showed us that
so there's a time where you have to include context as well
so when you're doing the contextless exercising
you can be about 10 to 15 an hour
in theory you should try to get about five hours of day
if you have at the time so what's five times 15
15 25 25 75 a day for about 18 months
because I still do this every day
and then on top of that the structured exercises
where you're including context to set expectations
for what price you do with you're building ideas
and you're identifying the more favourable areas to trade,
then you're probably only going to get two to three a day of them.
Eventually, you will do more of the structured engagement,
the context-based exercises rather than the random context-less exercises,
if that makes sense.
There's benefits to both of them, which I'll explain later.
The contextless, it validates price behaviour and fractal on a deep basis.
Like, forget that this is a one-minute chart.
Price just extended prices high and it filled.
That would happen on the weekly.
If I want to validate that this exists,
rather than waiting for it to happen on the weekly
and the daily, the one hour,
I can validate all the price behaviors on the one minute
very, very quickly.
And very frequently, they'll occur.
So here we had a price swing.
Price went to the core and responded off it.
That's one experience of price responding off core.
Just the same way it does on almost,
it does on every time frame.
You understand what I'm saying to say?
There's going to be a great,
the frequency of output of price behaviors on the one minute then on the on the let's say one hour
so in terms of validating price behavior you can get that quick that done quickly on the
lower time frame but it's a continuous process that doesn't stop because the one minute will
sometimes go into an environment like that it'll be highly highly inefficient like that sometimes
and things change and then the context inclusive exercising is one where you're going to be picking
parameters that you've seen work over time
let's say core areas of liquidity extensions
and whatnot price behaviors that work
and trying to assess the validity
the expectancy of those over a big
sample set. The problem with that is
let's say I'm only trading core area of liquidity
inefficient move into it
sideways pop into it. How often are you going to get that?
Maybe like once or twice a day or on a five minute swing.
On H1, two, three times a week.
Then the frequency of your exercises
has dropped and it takes a much longer
the time to collect that information.
So in terms of total exercises,
let me just try to give you something.
There's 22 trading days in a month.
Then in the year, there's 264 trading days.
Let's say you did the context less exercising every day,
five hours a day for a year.
That's 75 experiences a day times 264.
That's 19,800 exercises in a year.
I think that's right.
Yeah, yeah, that's about right.
and still probably that won't be enough
for honest with you
really 19,000
it's not enough
because you're going to be taking
shit exercises on them as well
then you have to validate
at this shit
trust me
rather than how many exercises it takes
put it into man hours
you will eventually
have spent the equivalent
of a year at charts
not a year looking at trading
a year at charts
so right now you spend
two hours in a call with me
a year at charts
if you spent about
eight hours a day
a year is something like
I think about 8,000 hours
24 times
365 yeah 8,700
yeah
divide that by 8,000 hours a day
it would take you a thousand days
three years
to reach a extremely proficient level
that does not mean
in the meantime you won't be trading life
and it doesn't mean that you can't
have in that meantime a good two-week period
where you smack it, bro.
And you make like 10, 15, 20 bikes.
That doesn't mean that can't happen.
But to reach that proficient level,
that high, high operational level
will take you about three years,
but I'll tell you for free now.
This is a performance.
Say again?
I can't believe you're all still doing it as well.
Yeah, you have to exercise
to maintain, to keep in sync.
Okay.
because I dread
I'm going to go away from Charles
for about six months
I'm going to come back
and I'll forget all the
the second level information
the intuitive
things I look at
that can't be explained
that deeply ingrained in my mind
it's quite easy to get out of work with it
so you have to maintain a process
where you're close to interact with Charles
so yeah
it doesn't matter whether you're 10 years down the line
you don't just suddenly reach a proficient
you don't reach a proficient level and that's it
you always have to maintain your skin
you always have to maintain your edge
there's always going to be small adjustments you're making
and you're always going to make mistakes you're fallible
what that means is like you can have the perfect process
that works you validated it
but your implementation of their as Zane
can fuck up
so at any given time you have to make small adjustments
okay that process is never going to stop
this game isn't
it's not what it's
made out to be in it
when I first heard about
Forex I thought oh you know what you get rich
rich in about a month or something like you know how people
sell it to you like on Instagram and stuff
I swear to God you could get rich in a month
but you have to have the big balls for it
willing to lose a lot of money and still have skill
you could get rich in a month
if you want to play it that way
you're likely
going to lose big pots and chunks at a time
I'm not saying that
That's how I am now.
That's how...
I'm saying, like, if you wanted to be that guy
who made a big chunk in a month,
what you need is capital behind you
and you need big balls.
You need to be able to stomach taking big losses in it.
Now, why can't you reach that level
after you can, you know,
it makes sense to try and reach that level
of taking the big chunks and taking the big risks
after you can take small risks successfully
in the first place.
I get it
Don't jump
In my opinion
There's no point
Jump into that level
If you can't stomach
Taking a loss
10 times in a row
On two or three pound of trade
There's no place for you
To fucking take
Try and take
A thousand pounds
Did you get it
Yeah
It's like you have to maintain
Like a small
Capital
Before you can
Yeah to be able to
Fucking
Yeah
So there's that
And
So yeah
I want to sit here
And say you can't make
Big Money
Quickly
people do do it but it also depends on personality who you are as a person
it's not really it's not really the most efficient way is it it it's the fastest way in it
but like it's not realistic for everyone in it yeah of course some people have the money gene
they can do it they don't give a thought they know that if they lose now they'll make it back
like there's a matter what they do they'll make those type of people is about what they do
they make money in then there's like more normal people you have to fucking
be even more prudent in it.
You can't do it mind in this.
Yeah, that's true.
But in either case, I'll give you
quite a simple barometer
for something, if it's easy
or not. If there's low barriers
to entry, you know, if someone's
enticing you to enter something
with the
trying to persuade you that's easy to make money in it,
if there's low barriers to entry,
the chance shit to you.
By that what I mean is if there's not
significant hurdles put in
your place to enter
into this new thing
that is likely
going to make you
a multimillionaire
quickly,
then they're trying to shit
to you.
Do you understand
what I'm trying to say?
There will always be
barriers to entry
on something
that's lucrative.
Think about
the real estate market.
if I wanted to be
a liquidity provider
tomorrow,
I need 50 million
balance sheet,
I can't do it
with a small amount of money.
Why?
Because the people
that are going to extend me
credit,
the banks
that are going to extend me
credit,
are going to
ask me, what is your business?
What is your turnover a year?
They don't want to give me credit
if I haven't got $50 million in the first place.
Can you see how there's a barrier to entry?
And we already know the equity providers
are the ones smacking it.
They're the ones that receive my flow,
that know about my flow,
that I know about all the information in the market
before everybody else.
Do you understand?
So if anybody ever tells you that this is easy,
ask them, what does it take?
And if they describe it as easy, low barriers to entry,
then they're trying to shit to you.
I'll give that fee for free.
Even like, it's called rent seeking,
where you look to maintain your market share
without increasing the size of the market, you know?
So like if I,
it's hard to think of an example.
An example is like taxis.
If you want to become a taxi driver,
you have to get a license.
You have to pay for that license.
You can't just go and start picking up random people.
They'll call it for safety reasons.
and for regularish reasons
but really it comes down to
you're having to pay
this person above you
money to drive a car
and pick people up
they're not increasing the size of the taxi market
they're just charging you a rent
so you can go and
provide taxi services
they're the greedy motherfuckers
if every time
you step out of your house
and you went on a different road
let's say
you drove in London
around city centre
they charge
you're a congestion charge
they charge a new rent
for you coming into the city
even
you get it
like these are things
put in your place
that act as hurdles
any single
industry that is lucrative
will have significant
anti-competition
type hurdles
in place
so think about FX
you can deposit
sometimes $10 10 pound
they give you
500 to one leverage
they practically
sometimes they give you bonuses
for putting in deposits
they practically
let you just open up an account
for nothing
why because the retail
brokers are smacking it off you
brof so yeah
it's unrealistic
that you know
you can even look at
regulatory data 70% of retail
clients about lose money
and they're likely
people that tell you it's easy to make money, you know?
Yeah, most likely.
It's not rough. This game, even if you look at it from the perspective of HFTs
and their ability to exploit information on a sub-second scale and transact a thousand times
before I click my button, they have access to more appropriate information about the true
price of pound before me, and they can act on it before me.
Very, very, very, very good.
Like, where's the edge?
There is no edge in trading on those short.
timeframes. For me at least
because I'm too slow. They'll trade ahead of me and
that, you know, so
if price is fundamentally undervalued
right now and it's supposed to
be here, the HFT will act on
and push you up there way before I click my button.
That's why you can't trade
breakouts anymore, bro. By the time
that breakouts
seen on our screen, the volatility
is finished, it's gone, has happened.
So, yeah, the work
is too efficient for us. It's efficiently
inefficient.